A Finding Aid to the Peter Hopkins Papers, 1823-2001, bulk 1935-1994, in the Archives of American Art AAA.hopkpete
Archives of American Art
Peter Hopkins papers
bulk 1935-1994
1823-2001
AAA.hopkpete
Archives of American Art
2.4 Linear feet
The Peter Hopkins papers measure 2.4 linear feet and date from 1823-2001, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1935-1994. Writings, letters and diaries make up most of the collection. Printed materials relate to exhibitions of Hopkins' artwork and theatrical performances of his wife, Gertrude Beach Hopkins. There also are writings by both Hopkins and his wife that appeared in the Christian Science Monitor. Of particular interest is a group of vintage family photographs and family papers dating from the 19th century, as well as diaries Hopkins kept while traveling and working in a mental hospital in inland China in the mid 1930s.
Hopkins, Peter, 1911-1999
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in 2009 by the artist's neighbor, James McGuane.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical Note
Peter Hopkins (1911-1999) was an artist, educator and writer, who lived and worked in Greenwich Village in New York City.
Hopkins, the son of a theatrical producer, was educated at the prestigious Hotchkiss School. Despite limited formal education, he became a lecturer at the Art Students League of New York and an instructor at the New York Phoenix School of Design. Hopkins' paintings were exhibited in the 1950s-1960s. Hopkins wrote numerous unpublished manuscripts and was a columnist with the Christian Science Monitor in the 1970s. He was married to Gertrude Beach Hopkins (d.1997) an actress, who in later years was a poet.
Scope and Content Note
The Peter Hopkins papers measure 2.4 linear feet and date from 1823-2001, with the bulk of materials dating from 1935-1994. Writings, letters and diaries make up most of the collection. Printed materials relate to exhibitions of Hopkins' artwork and theatrical performances of his wife, Gertrude Beach Hopkins. There also are writings by both Hopkins and his wife that appeared in the Christian Science Monitor. Of particular interest is a group of vintage family photographs and family papers dating from the 19th century, as well as diaries Hopkins kept while traveling and working in a mental hospital in inland China in the mid 1930s.
Manuscripts by Hopkins include his theories on perspective (the subject of his lectures at The Art Students League of New York) and the artistic methods of great masters. Hopkins also wrote about his theories concerning anthropological matters, world politics, over population, and the meaning of life. Much of Hopkins' correspondence concerns his efforts to explore career opportunities and find audiences for his ideas and writings.
The collection contains one intact scrapbook consisting of materials spanning Hopkins' art career, a substantial quantity of photographs and slides of Hopkins' paintings, some drawings and sketches, and a few sound and video recordings. In addition, there are writings by fathers of the couple, Charles R. Hopkins and Joseph Beach.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 11 series. Records are generally arranged by material type and chronologiclly thereafter.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1823-1995 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1934-2001 (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings, 1908-1997 (Boxes 1-2; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 4: Diaries, 1945-1998 (Box 2; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 5: Subject Files, 1966-1990 (Box 2; 3 folders)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1945-1980 (Box 2; 2 folders)
Series 7: Scrapbook, 1949-1997 (Box 2; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 8: Artwork, 1943-circa 1980s (Box 2; 1 folder)
Series 9: Sketchbooks, 1963-1982 (Box 2; 2 folders)
Series 10: Photographic Materials, 1864-1990s (Box 3; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 11: Sound and Video Recordings, circa 1976-1977 (Box 3; 0.3 linear feet)
Art Students League (New York, N.Y.) -- Faculty; Beach, Joseph; Hopkins, Charles; Art--Philosophy; Art--Study and teaching; Authors--New York (State)--New York; Diaries; Drawings; Educators--New York (State)--New York; Paianters--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketches
- Biographical Materials, 1823-1995; Series 1; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Hopkins' biographical materials include 2 address books, a New York State Certificate of Literacy, and various resumes and letters of recommendation. Among the family papers are a letter written in 1823 by Elihu Roberts to his cousin, Solomon, a page from "The Beach Family Journal" noting the the Beach Ancestry of Sir Winston Churchill, and materials relating to the lives of Hopkins' father, grandfather and father-in-law.
  - Miscellaneous, 1945-1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Family Papers, 1823-1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1934-2001; Series 2; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  The collection contains a large quantity of correspondence and letters. Family correspondence includes a couple of letters from the Norman Rockwell family, discussion of family grievances, and love letters from Gertrude to Peter. There is correspondence with author Tim Joyner concerning illustrations Hopkins submitted for Joyner's book about Magellan. Also, there are letters by Hopkins to notables such as Vice President Al Gore, physicist Steven Hawking, and United Nations Secretary General U Thant, in which Hopkins gives his thoughts on issues of the time.
  - Family Correspondence, undated; 1935-1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with Gil T., 1934-1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with Tim Joyner, 1985-1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence Regarding the Sale of Art, undated; 1953-1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence Regarding Legal Matters, 1960-2001 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1938-1994 (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
  - Letters from Antoinette Mary Wilson, undated; 1956-1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters from Gertrude Beach Hopkins, 1953-1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters from Lynne Fontanne, 1958-1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters Regarding Job Applications, 1969-1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Writings, 1908-1997; Series 3; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Writings include Hopkins' Christian Science Monitor columns, manuscripts he drafted on subjects of contemporary interest, and essays concerning detailed analyses of perspective in drawing. There also are writings concerning China in the 1930s, which may be rare in content. Writings by family members also are part of this series.
  - By Peter Hopkins (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, undated; 1983; 1968; 1937; 1934 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - China, 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "Anthropological Double Take,", 1953; 1968; 1981; undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "The United States and the World, an Overview,", 1965; 1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Population and Geonomics, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Christian Science Monitor Articles, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Draft Articles for Christian Science Monitor, 1976-1978; undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Perspectives in the Universe," "What's in a Name,", 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "Old Master Painting Techniques,", circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - "Perspective by Calculator,", 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - "New Design for Living,", 1982 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - "Measured Perspective Drawing,", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - "Perspective Drawing,", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "The Purpose of Life,", 1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - By Others (Box 2)
    - Gertrude Beach Hopkins, Poems, 1974-1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Gertrude Beach Hopkins, Miscellaneous, 1994-1997 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Charles Robert Hopkins, Journal, 1908-1914 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Joseph Beach, "Stranger in the Creek,", before 1960 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Diaries, 1945-1998; Series 4; 0.3 Linear feet Box 2
  Volume 1 contains sporadic entries dated 1987-1989 recorded in a weekly planner. Volumes 2-6 record daily domestic and local activities with some drafts of letters and newspaper clippings attached. Volume 7 shows greater focus on health concerns and records the passing of Hopkins' wife, Gertrude. Volume 8 records the quotidian concerns of an elderly man.
  - Loose Pages, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Volume 1, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Volume 2, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Volume 3, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Volume 4, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Volume 5, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Volume 6, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Volume 7, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Volume 8, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Subject Files, 1966-1990; Series 5; 3 Folders Box 2
  The New York Phoenix School of Design teaching materials contain information about the school, course and curriculum summaries, business correspondence and a roll book. The Art Students League of New York lecture notes include drawings and perspective calculations, a list of paint colors, and printed materials by "C.C.B." detailing perspective with 1 point, 2 points and bird's eye analyses and plans. The Museum of the City of New York materials acknowledge Hopkins' gift of his painting Riot in Union Square and advise of its use in a 1990 exhibition.
  - New York Phoenix School of Design Teaching, 1966-1977 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Art Students League of New York Lectures, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Museum of the City of New York, "Riot in Union Square,", 1966-1990 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Printed Materials, 1945-1980; Series 6; 2 Folders Box 2
  Printed material includes original and photocopied items relating to group exhibitions in which Hopkins participated, and one man shows at the Ward Eggleston Galleries in New York City. Also found are theater programs from plays in which Gertrude Beach Hopkins performed.
  - Exhibitions, 1947-1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    includes photocopies
  - Gertrude Beach Hopkins Dramatic Performances, 1945; 1951; undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Scrapbook, 1949-1997; Series 7; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  Hopkins' scrapbook contains mostly printed materials but also some letters and photographs, all of which document the highlights of his career as a painter and art educator.
  - Scrapbook, 1949-1997 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Artwork, 1943-circa 1980s; Series 8; 1 Folders Box 2
  Found here are loose drawings and sketches, some of which are photocopies. Most of the work is in pencil and does not appear very developed.
  - Drawings and Sketches, 1943; 1956; circa 1960s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Sketchbooks, 1963-1982; Series 9; 2 Folders Box 2
  Found are two volumes of sketches. The earlier book has more developed ink drawings.
  - Sketchbooks, Volume 1, 1963; undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Sketchbooks, Volume 2, 1982; undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Photographic Materials, 1864-1990s; Series 10; 0.4 Linear feet Box 3
  Included are photographs, negatives and slides of Hopkins' paintings. Of note are 19th century tintypes of family members and a cabinet card of January 7, 1864, showing ancestor Elihu Roberts. Late 19th century and early 20th century photographs, most without identifying notes, are in black and white or tinted. There also are professional theatrical photographs of Gertrude Beach Hopkins from the 1940s and miscellaneous snapshots of family and friends.
  - Vintage Photographs of People, undated; 1864 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Photographs of People, 1885-1917 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Photographs of Family and Friends, undated; 1986-1991; circa 1940s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - Photographs of Gertrude Beach Hopkins, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Artwork, Photographs and Negatives, 1940s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Artwork, Slides, 1950s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Artwork, Miscellaneous Photographs, undated; after 1993 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Artwork, Photographs, 1940s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Sound and Video Recordings, circa 1976-1977; Series 11; 0.3 Linear feet Box 3
  This series contains an undated video recording of Hopkins' wife Gerturde, a sound recording of a 1976 "workshop" and 3 unidentified recordings.
  - Video Recording of "Gertrude,", undated; 1 Videocassettes (Box 3, Folder 5)
    VHS
  - Unidentified Sound Recordings, 1976-1977; undated; 3 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - December, 1976 Workshop and Unidentified Sound Recordings, undated; 4 sound tape reels (Box 3, Folder 7)